Guide to the Abe Fortas Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence and Topical Files, 1935-1983; Series II
  - U-V, 1958-1971 (Box 124, Folder 408)
  - Udall, Stewart L.
    See: Puerto Rico; Sánchez-Vilella, Roberto; Verity, C. William, Jr.
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1947-1981 (Box 124, Folder 409)
  - University of Chicago School of Law
    See: Ka; Series VI. University of Chicago, School of Law
  - Valenti, Jack, 1973-1977 (Box 124, Folder 410)
    See also: Douglas, William O.; Stern, Isaac and Vera
  - Van Buren, Abigail, 1976-1977 (Box 124, Folder 411)
  - Vance, Cyrus R.
    See: McGovern, George; Series VI. President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity in the Armed Forces
  - Vander Jagt, Guy
  - Verity, C. William, Jr., 1965-1968 (Box 124, Folder 412)
  - Vieth, G. Duane
    See: Series III. Books-- Concerning Dissent and Civil Disobedience, Correspondence (personal), V-Z; Speeches--Justifications Under the Robinson-Patman Act, New York State Bar Antitrust Symposium; Series IV. Correspondence--Personal--S-Z
  - Virginia Chamber Orchestra
  - Wa-We, 1956-1981 (Box 124, Folder 413)
  - Walker, James W., Jr., 1971-1980 (Box 124, Folder 414)
    See also: Series III. Articles--"Chief Justice Warren: The Enigma of Leadership"
  - Warnke, Paul C.
  - Warren, Earl, 1956-1981 (Box 124, Folder 415 - 416)
    See also: Douglas, William O.--Douglas Anniversary Convocation; Johnson, Lyndon Baines; McGuire, Rebekah L.; Series IV. Clark, Tom C.; Inaugural Concert 1965; Kennedy assassination, John F.
  - Washington Performing Arts Society, 1974-1982 (Box 124, Folder 417)
  - Watson, W. Marvin, 1971-1976 (Box 124, Folder 418)
  - Wechsler, Herbert
  - Weeks, Edward
    See: Rykens, Paul
  - Weiner, Joseph L.
    See: Palestine; Series IV. Correspondence--Personal--S-Z
  - Weisl, Edwin L., 1957-1967 (Box 124, Folder 419)
    See also: Series IV. Ewig, Arthur
  - Wellington, Harry H.
  - Wels, Richard H., 1975 (Box 124, Folder 420)
  - West Publishing Company, 1965-1966 (Box 124, Folder 421)
  - Westwood, Howard C., 1966 (Box 125, Folder 422)
  - Wg-Wu, 1956-1981 (Box 125, Folder 423)
  - Wharton, John F.
    See: Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison; Series IV. Chase, Lucia
  - Wheeler, Stanton
  - White, Byron R., 1961-1977 (Box 125, Folder 424)
    See also: Peru trip; Porter, Paul A. and Kathleen Winsor; Series IV. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Inaugural Concert 1965
  - Whitehair, Francis P., 1956-1981 (Box 125, Folder 425)
    See also: Series III. Books-- Concerning Dissent and Civil Disobedience, Correspondence (personal), V-Z; Series IV. Correspondence--Personal--S-Z
  - Wickeneden, Elizabeth, 1963-1982 (Box 125, Folder 426)
    See also: Goldschmidt, Arthur ("Tex") and Elizabeth Wickenden Goldschmidt
  - Williams, Maggie, 1966-1982 (Box 125, Folder 427)
    See also: Series VI. Kennedy Center, Stevens, Roger L.
  - Wisdom, John Minor
  - Wolfensohn, James D.
    See: Charitable contributions; Hessler, Curtis Alan; Stern, Isaac and Vera; Wg-Wn; Series VI. Carnegie Hall Corporation and Society
  - Wolfgang, Marvin E.
    See: American Academy of Political and Social Science
  - Wolfson, Louis E., 1966-1977 (Box 125, Folder 428 - 429)
    See also: Series III. Speeches--[No title], Convocation, Jewish Theological Seminary, 1965; To Fulfill the Constitution, Temple Beth Am
  - Woodfin, Gene M. and Judith F., 1970-1976 (Box 125, Folder 430)
    See also: Series III. Articles--"The Case Against Capital Punishment"
  - Wouk, Herman, 1967-1980 (Box 125, Folder 431)
    See also: Series VI. Kennedy Center Productions, Inc.
  - Wright, Charles Alan, 1969-1973 (Box 125, Folder 432)
    See also: Rodell, Fred; Yale Law School
  - Wright, J. Skelly
    See: Brennan, William J., Jr.; Douglas, William O.
  - Wright, Jim
  - Wurlitzer, Lee and family, 1964-1979, undated (Box 125, Folder 433)
  - Y, 1968-1982 (Box 125, Folder 434)
  - Yale Law School, 1935-1981, undated
    - Course in "Legal Principles of Competitive Economics" (Box 125, Folder 435-436)
    - January 1946-August 1947 (Box 125, Folder 437 - 438)
    - August-November 1947 (Box 126, Folder 439 - 440)
    - Moot Court of Appeals, 1955-1956 (Box 126, Folder 441)
    - Citation of Merit, 1965-1966 (Box 126, Folder 442)
  - Yale Political Union, 1974-1979 (Box 126, Folder 443)
  - Yale University library, 1973-1982 (Box 126, Folder 444)
  - Yarmolinsky, Adam
    See: Maggin, Donald L.; Series IV. Johnson, Lyndon Baines--Writings and speeches--War on poverty address
  - Young, Lawrence A., 1981-1982 (Box 126, Folder 445)
  - Z, 1966-1982 (Box 126, Folder 446)
  - Zimroth, Peter L., 1967-1975 (Box 126, Folder 447)
    See also: Series III. Speeches--[No title], Yale Law Journal banquet, 1966
- Writings, 1944-1982; Series III
  The writings series is divided into three sub-sections: books, articles, and speeches. The folders related to Fortas's books are arranged alphabetically. The folders related to his articles and speeches are arranged chronologically. Published articles are differentiated from unpublished articles by the use of quotation marks and the inclusion of the name of the periodical in which the article was published. If known, the title of the article or speech is given in the folder description. The range and depth of the materials that constitute this series vary widely. Some folders contain an extensive record of the speech or writing, including the initial invitation to speak or produce an article, background materials, and multiple drafts. Many files also contain extensive correspondence with representatives of the host organization or editors; newspaper clippings and reviews that resulted from the speech or writing; and, in some cases, considerable and substantive correspondence from a wide array of people. Beyond letters from his readers or members of his audience, it was also Fortas's habit to send copies of his speeches and writings to friends, acquaintances, business associates, government officials, academics, and public figures. Many files contain carbon copies of the brief notes accompanying the speech or article. Other files in this series are less complete. In cases where the text of the speech or writing itself is missing, a note of "Background materials only" has been added to the folder title.
  The earliest writings in the series date from Fortas's final months as undersecretary of the Interior. During this time he often spoke for Secretary of the Interior Harold L. Ickes, his boss and early mentor. Fortas also often spoke for President Roosevelt and for the Democratic Party, appearing at campaign rallies and on radio programs to support Democratic policies and politicians. He also expressed his own views, particularly against the coming excesses of the Cold War, and for a strong and meaningful international force, such as he helped to develop in the United Nations, in an attempt to avoid a relapse into world war.
  As founding partner of a powerful and respected law firm, Fortas spoke as often on matters of human rights as on the business and finance questions facing his expanding base of corporate clients. One of his abiding interests, which is strongly reflected in this series, was that of the interaction of law and psychiatry. The files document Fortas's work related to his appointment in 1954 as counsel to Monte Durham in the case of Durham v. United States. This case helped transform the law of criminal responsibility as it relates to mental illness. Fortas was a vocal opponent of the "red baiting" and "red hunting" tactics of Senator Joseph McCarthy and his allies, and this is clearly reflected in his firm's representation of many of those accused by McCarthy and others. Fortas was also a highly sought after toastmaster, and his ready wit is documented and greatly praised in these files.
  In the years just prior to his nomination to the Supreme Court, Fortas's stature and popularity increased greatly, both because of his status as a personal friend, and legal and political advisor to President Lyndon B. Johnson, and as one of the nation's most respected corporate lawyers. This increasing prominence was evident in the large number of public appearances Fortas was asked to make, and the articles that he was asked to contribute to a variety of publications, both scholarly and popular. During this period, Fortas also addressed America's growing racial difficulties, both in the northern cities and across his native south.
  Once on the Court, Fortas continued to have an active public personae, becoming one of the most visible members of Chief Justice Earl Warren's dynamic court. While on the Supreme Court, Fortas was given a number of honorary degrees, and invited to give prestigious lectures (some of which later were published as articles), often giving his views on the nature and meaning of the Constitution, and the Supreme Court's unique role in interpreting that document. He was also a leading analyst during this period of the civil and campus unrest that was sweeping the nation. His book, Concerning Dissent and Civil Disobedience was widely reviewed, and it led to a great deal of correspondence, both from the general public and from those known personally to Fortas. He was prized as a critic of extremists on both sides of the national and international campus battles, and spoke at dozens of educational institutions across the country.
  After the withdrawal of his name for the position of chief justice and his subsequent resignation from the Supreme Court, Fortas's production and presence were little diminished. He continued to write and speak extensively on civil disobedience and civil rights. He returned to his abiding interest in the issue of antitrust law, developed through his legal practice, and through his long and formative relationship with William O. Douglas. He also addressed matters related to the Watergate scandal and the question of presidential impeachment, Puerto Rican politics and business, and the death penalty.
  - Books
    - Concerning Dissent and Civil Disobedience
      - Correspondence (personal), A-Z, 1966-1972 (Box 127, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Background materials, including correspondence (public) and reviews, 1966-1972 (Box 127, Folder 7 - 12)
      - Drafts
        - March 1966-July 1967 (Box 127, Folder 13)
        - n.d. (Box 128, Folder 14)
      - Reader's Digest
        - French edition, 1968 (Box 128, Folder 15)
        - German edition [condensed], 1968 (Box 128, Folder 16)
        - Iberian edition [condensed], 1968 (Box 128, Folder 17)
        - Italian edition [condensed], 1968 (Box 128, Folder 18)
        - Japanese edition [condensed], 1968 (Box 128, Folder 19)
    - The Social Revolution: Crisis and Promise [unpublished book manuscript], 1970 (Box 128, Folder 20 - 24)
  - Articles
    - These Are the Boys [unpublished], [1943?] (Box 129, Folder 25)
    - Check and Double-Check: Congress and the Executive [unpublished], [1943?] (Box 129, Folder 26)
    - "An American Land Policy," The Progressive, 1944 (Box 129, Folder 27)
    - Government by Check and Double-Check [unpublished], 1945 (Box 129, Folder 28)
    - "Puerto Rico- Problem Child," This Week, New York Herald Tribune [also published as "Puerto Rico Challenge to Americans' Belief in Others' Freedom," The Washington Post ], 1945 (Box 129, Folder 29)
    - "Effects of Prejudice," The Washington Post, 1945 (Box 129, Folder 30)
    - "The Art of Living Together," The Young Democrat [also published as "The Atomic Age and Survival," Washington Daily News ], 1946 (Box 129, Folder 31)
    - "An Appreciation: The Psychiatry of Enduring Peace and Social Progress," Psychiatry, 1946 (Box 129, Folder 32)
    - "What Should the United States Do About Pacific Bases?," National Peace Conference Bulletin, 1946 (Box 129, Folder 33)
    - "The Search for Certainty," Psychiatry, 1946 (Box 129, Folder 34)
    - "Youth Looks Ahead: We Are Rolling Down the Path to War," St. Louis Post-Dispatch, 1948 (Box 129, Folder 35)
    - "The Legal Interview," Psychiatry, 1952 (Box 129, Folder 36)
    - "Outside the Law," The Atlantic Monthly, 1953 (Box 129, Folder 37)
    - "Outside the Law," Connecticut Bar Journal, 1953 (Box 129, Folder 38)
    - "The Washington Lawyer," by Charles A. Horsky, Northwestern University Law Review [book review], 1953 (Box 129, Folder 39)
    - "Abusive Practices of Investigating Committees," Notre Dame Lawyer, 1954 (Box 130, Folder 40)
    - "The Age of Suspicion," by James Wechsler, Stanford Law Review [book review], 1954 (Box 130, Folder 41)
    - "The Fifth Amendment: Nemo Tenetur Prodere Seipsum," The Journal of the Cleveland Bar Association, 1954 (Box 130, Folder 42 - 43)
    - "Affirmative Legal Defenses," How to Comply with the Antitrust Laws, 1954 (Box 130, Folder 44)
    - "Implications of Durham's Case," American Journal of Psychiatry, 1957 (Box 130, Folder 45)
    - "'Anti-trust' in the United States," Progress, 1957 (Box 130, Folder 46)
    - "Foreword," to Antitrust Laws by A. D. Neale, 1961 (Box 130, Folder 47)
    - "Freedom and the Criminal Process," The New Republic [book review], 1961 (Box 130, Folder 48)
    - "Small Business, Mergers, and Section 7 of the Clayton Act," University of Detroit Law Journal, 1961 (Box 130, Folder 49)
    - Lawyers and Social Revolutions, New York Times Magazine [unpublished], 1962 (Box 130, Folder 50)
    - "Sacco, Vanzetti - and Justice," The Washington Post [book review], 1962 (Box 130, Folder 51)
    - "America's Electrical Price Conspiracy," The Lawyer, 1962 (Box 131, Folder 52)
    - "The Consequences of Gideon," The Legal Aid Briefcase, 1963 (Box 131, Folder 53)
    - "Mr. Justice Douglas," Yale Law Journal, 1964 (Box 131, Folder 54)
    - "Portents for New Antitrust Policy," The Antitrust Bulletin, 1965 (Box 131, Folder 55)
    - "Foreword," Do You Solemnly Swear? by Louis B. Heller, 1966-1968 (Box 131, Folder 56)
    - "Thou Shalt Not Ration Justice," Connecticut Bar Journal [includes photograph], 1966 (Box 131, Folder 57)
    - "Equal Rights -- For Whom?," New York University Law Review [also published in New York Law Journal ], 1967 (Box 131, Folder 58)
    - "The Limits of Civil Disobedience," New York Times Magazine, 1968 (Box 131, Folder 59)
    - "Dangers to the Rule of Law," American Bar Association Journal, 1968 (Box 131, Folder 60)
    - "The Fight for Due Process," Case and Comment, 1968 (Box 131, Folder 61)
    - "The History of Dissent," New York Times [written for inclusion in a film strip], 1968 (Box 131, Folder 62)
    - Syracuse Law Review [letter of congratulations], 1969 (Box 131, Folder 63)
    - "Rights" Aren't Enough [unpublished article for the New York Times ?], [1969?] (Box 131, Folder 64)
    - "The Coming Assault on Individual Rights," Multi: The Magazine of Case Western Reserve University, 1979 (Box 131, Folder 65)
    - "Thurman Arnold and the Theatre of Law," Yale Law Journal [also published in the New York Times ], 1970 (Box 131, Folder 66 - 67)
    - "The Patent System in Distress," IDEA, 1971 (Box 131, Folder 68)
    - "The Para[lawyer] Principle," New York Times, 1971 (Box 131, Folder 69)
    - "New Threats to Individual Liberty," Saint Louis University Law Review, 1971 (Box 132, Folder 70)
    - "The Frontier Between Antitrust Law and the Securities Market," Illinois Bar Journal, 1972 (Box 132, Folder 71)
    - "Lyndon Johnson," New York Times, 1973 (Box 132, Folder 72)
    - "The Constitution and the Presidency," Washington Law Review [also published as "Mr. Nixon and the Constitution," New York Times ], 1974 (Box 132, Folder 73 - 77)
    - "The Constitution and the Presidency," Washington Law Review [also published as "Mr. Nixon and the Constitution," New York Times ], 1974 (Box 133, Folder 78 - 80)
    - "Foreword" to The New Private Practice by Allan Ashman, National Legal Aid and Defender Association Briefcase [also published in the New York Times ], 1972 (Box 133, Folder 81)
    - "The Non-Conformists," ADL Bulletin, 1973 (Box 133, Folder 82)
    - Go East Young Man: The Early Years by William O. Douglas, New York University Law Review [book review], 1974 (Box 133, Folder 83)
    - "The U.S. Investment Environment: The Legislative and Regulatory Framework," The Conference Board Record, 1974 (Box 133, Folder 84)
    - An Untimely Constitutional Dissent [unpublished], 1974 (Box 133, Folder 85)
    - "The Law," TV Guide, 1974 (Box 133, Folder 86)
    - "Strengthening Government to Cope with the Future," The New Republic, 1974 (Box 133, Folder 87)
    - "Chief Justice Warren: The Enigma of Leadership," Yale Law Journal, 1975 (Box 133, Folder 88)
    - "William O. Douglas: An Appreciation," Indiana Law Journal, 1975-1976 (Box 133, Folder 89)
    - "The Case Against Capital Punishment," the New York Times Magazine, 1977 (Box 134, Folder 90 - 93)
    - "The Changing Role for the United States in the World," LES Nouvelles: Journal of the Licensing Executives Society, 1977 (Box 134, Folder 94)
    - "Age Discrimination in Employment Under Federal Law," Aging and Work, 1978 (Box 134, Folder 95 - 96)
    - "William O. Douglas: A Eulogy," Yale Law Journal, 1980 (Box 134, Folder 97)
    - The Right to Counsel Since Gideon v. Wainwright [unpublished], 1980 (Box 134, Folder 98)
    - President Reagan and the Caribbean Basin Initiative, Foreign Policy [unpublished], 1982 (Box 134, Folder 99)
  - Speeches
    - Our Generation, Affiliated Young Democrats of New York State, 1944 (Box 135, Folder 100)
    - Public Investment for the Peoples Profit, WWDC [radio broadcast], 1944 (Box 135, Folder 101)
    - Don't Forget the Elephant, Young Voters for Roosevelt, 1944 (Box 135, Folder 102)
    - Full Employment or What Kind of a Nation?, Philadelphia Industrial Union Council, C.I.O., 1945 (Box 135, Folder 103)
    - The Economic Base for Democratic Living, All-Philadelphia Conference on Social Work, 1945 (Box 135, Folder 104)
    - The Art of Living Together, City College of New York, 1945 (Box 135, Folder 105)
    - United Nations' Responsibility for Dependent People, Rutgers University [background materials only], 1946 (Box 135, Folder 106)
    - An Approach to Progressive Policy, Southwestern College at Memphis, 1946 (Box 135, Folder 107 - 108)
    - Is Big Business Too Big?, America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1946 (Box 135, Folder 109 - 110)
    - Russia, Foreign Affairs Forum, WINX [radio broadcast], 1946 (Box 136, Folder 111)
    - To Live in Peace, WMAL [radio broadcast], 1946 (Box 136, Folder 112)
    - Can Business Overcome the Challenge of Inflation?, People's Platform, CBS [radio broadcast], 1946 (Box 136, Folder 113)
    - Racial Condition in the Postwar South, Southern Conference on Human Welfare [background materials only], 1946 (Box 136, Folder 114)
    - Armistice Day, Jewish War Veterans, 1946 (Box 136, Folder 115)
    - Conference on America's foreign policy and maintaining peace, University of Chicago [background materials only], 1946 (Box 136, Folder 116)
    - The Challenge of Community Living, Brotherhood of Washington Hebrew Congregation, 1947 (Box 136, Folder 117)
    - Democracy in Retreat: Elephants and Elephantism, Tulane University, 1947 (Box 136, Folder 118)
    - Economic Security and Community Tensions, Philadelphia Jewish Community Relations Council, 1947 (Box 136, Folder 119)
    - A Perspective of Labor-Management Relations, Rutgers Labor Institute, 1947 (Box 136, Folder 120)
    - Invitations to speak or write, 1946-1947 (Box 136, Folder 121)
    - Is the Truman Program Moving Towards Socialism?, Court of Current Issues, Dumont Television Network, 1949 (Box 136, Folder 122)
    - Is Freedom of Speech Threatened in America?, America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1950 (Box 136, Folder 123)
    - Constitution--Conscience--Communism, American Law Institute, 1953 (Box 136, Folder 124)
    - Civil Liberties in the United States, Anti-Defamation League of B'nai Brith [background materials only], 1953 (Box 136, Folder 125)
    - Ethical Responsibilities of Government, Rutgers University [background materials only], 1953 (Box 136, Folder 126)
    - Methods of Committees Investigating Subversion: A Critique, University of Notre Dame [includes photograph], 1953 (Box 137, Folder 127)
    - The Responsibilities of Politics, The Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1953 (Box 137, Folder 128)
    - Justifications Under the Robinson-Patman Act, New York State Bar Antitrust Symposium, 1954 (Box 137, Folder 129)
    - The Role of Counsel for the Witness in a Public Investigation, Harvard Student Bar Association, 1954 (Box 137, Folder 130)
    - A Time for Putting Together Again, William Alanson White Institute, 1954 (Box 137, Folder 131)
    - Justifications Under the Robinson-Patman Act, University of Cincinnati College of Law, 1954 (Box 137, Folder 132)
    - Durham decision [background materials only], 1955 (Box 137, Folder 133)
    - Durham case, Conference on Insanity and the Law, University of Chicago, 1955 (Box 137, Folder 134)
    - The Defense of Insanity in a Criminal Case, American Bar Association [background materials only], 1955 (Box 138, Folder 135)
    - Introductory remarks, American Veterans Committee, 1955 (Box 138, Folder 136)
    - Implications of Durham's Case, American Psychiatric Association, 1955 (Box 138, Folder 137)
    - Interrelationships Between Law and Psychiatry, Washington Psychiatric Society, 1956 (Box 138, Folder 138)
    - Law and insanity [background materials only], 1956-1959 (Box 138, Folder 139 - 140)
    - The Durham Rule, Junior Bar Section, Bar Association of the District of Columbia [television script], 1958 (Box 138, Folder 141)
    - The Rule in Durham's Case, Federal Bar Association, 1958 (Box 138, Folder 142)
    - Doing Business Under the Robinson-Patman Act: Brokerage, Advertising Allowances, and Services, Practising Law Institute, 1958 (Box 138, Folder 143)
    - Law and psychiatry [background materials only], 1958-1959 (Box 138, Folder 144)
    - And Now for a Few Closing Remarks by President Eisenhower..., 1959 (Box 138, Folder 145)
    - The Grievances of the Small Business Man -- A Bill of Particulars, American Bar Association, Section on Antitrust Laws, 1960 (Box 138, Folder 146)
    - Not a New Deal But a New Zeal, Memphis Rotary Club [background materials only], 1961 (Box 139, Folder 147)
    - American Bar Association, Section on Antitrust Laws, 1963 (Box 139, Folder 148)
    - Columbia Law Review dinner, 1964 (Box 139, Folder 149)
    - Yale Law School Alumni Association, 1964 (Box 139, Folder 150)
    - Memphis and Shelby County Bar Association, 1964 (Box 139, Folder 151)
    - Lawlessness in the Streets, Federal Bar Association [excerpts printed as "Courts, Crime and the Federal Lawyer," The Forum ], 1964 (Box 139, Folder 152)
    - Portents for New Anti-Trust Policy, Corporate Counsel Institute [background materials only], 1964 (Box 139, Folder 153)
    - Alumni Association dinner, Boston College Law School, 1965 (Box 139, Folder 154)
    - Invitations to speak or write [includes photographs], 1965-1967 (Box 139, Folder 155)
      See also: Series IV. Writing offers
    - Federal Bar Association, 1965 (Box 139, Folder 156)
    - 18th Judicial District Bar Association, 1965 (Box 139, Folder 157)
    - Convocation, Jewish Theological Seminary, 1965 (Box 139, Folder 158)
    - Animal Welfare Institute, 1965 (Box 139, Folder 159)
    - In Memoriam: Louis Eisenstein, 1966 (Box 140, Folder 160)
    - National Conference of the American Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training [includes photograph], 1966 (Box 140, Folder 161)
    - Constitutional Rights Foundation, 1966 (Box 140, Folder 162)
    - Yale Law School Association of Washington, D.C., 1966 (Box 140, Folder 163)
    - Brandeis Memorial Lecture, Brandeis University, 1966 (Box 140, Folder 164)
    - Yale Law Journal banquet, 1966 (Box 140, Folder 165)